Boris Brasol Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Boris Brasol Papers 1919-1954
MSS13672
Brasol, Boris, 1885-1963
22,000 items
64 containers
25.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Russian author and critic, criminologist, and lawyer. Correspondence, speeches, drafts and typescripts, notes, memoranda, and other material relating to Russia and the Soviet Union and to Brasol's writings and work as a criminologist.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bernstein, Herman, 1876-1935--Trials, litigation, etc.; Brasol, Boris, 1885-1963.; Dostoyevsky, Fyodor, 1821-1881. Dnevnik pisateli︠a︡. English.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947--Trials, litigation, etc.; Holland, Vyvyan Beresford, 1886-1967--Correspondence.; Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1868-1918--Assassination.; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849.; Romanov, House of.; Von Koeppen, Vladimir.; Wade, Allan, 1881-1955--Correspondence.; Wheelock, John Hall, 1886-1978--Correspondence.; Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900--Correspondence.; Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900.
Organizations
Columbia University. School of Law.; Edgar Allan Poe Society of Baltimore (Md.)
Subjects
Antisemitism--United States.; Criminal investigation--Europe.; Criminology.; Criticism.; Jews--United States.; Russian literature.; Soviet literature.; Zionism.
Places
Russia.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.
Titles
Protocols of the wise men of Zion.
Occupations
Authors.; Criminologists.; Critics.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Boris Brasol, Russian author and critic, criminologist, and lawyer, were given to the Library of Congress by Brasol between 1938 and 1959. An additional gift was made in 1955 by Charles Scribner's Sons.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Boris Brasol are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1885, Mar. 31 Born, Poltava, Russia
1908 B.L., University of Petrograd, Petrograd, Russia
1910 1916 Prosecuting attorney in the Russian Ministry of Justice
1912 Studied forensic science, Lausanne University, Lausanne, Switzerland
1914 1916 Served as second lieutenant, Imperial Russian Guard, on the Polish front
1916 Russian representative in the United States, Interallied Conference
1917 Stayed in the United States as an emigrant following the October Revolution in Russia
1918 1963 Practised law, New York, N.Y., specializing in Russian law, while pursuing a career as a literary critic and criminologist
1920 Published Socialism vs. Civilization. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons
1921 Published The World at the Cross Roads. Boston: Small, Maynard and Co.
1922 Published The Balance Sheet of Sovietism. New York: Duffield
1927 Published Elements of Crime. New York: Oxford University Press
1934 Published The Mighty Three: Poushkin, Gogol, Dostoievsky. New York: William Farquhar Payson
1938 Published Oscar Wilde: the Man, the Artist, the Martyr. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons
1949 Translated Fyodor Dostoyevsky's The Diary of a Writer. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons
1963, Mar. 19 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Boris Leo Brasol (1885-1963) span the years 1919-1954. The collection consists of correspondence, drafts and typescripts, notes, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and miscellaneous material relating to Russia and the Soviet Union, criminology, the Zionist movement, and Brasol's writings and various subjects of his literary criticism. The papers are in English and Russian and are organized into the following series: Political Correspondence, Personal Correspondence, Anti-Soviet Campaign, Scrapbook, Post-Revolutionary Russia, Legal File, Vladimir von Koeppen File, Speeches, Literary File, Newspaper Clippings, and Addition.
Subjects of interest include investigations into the assassinations of the Romanovs and crime detection in European countries as compiled by the Criminological Survey of the Columbia University Law School. The Literary File contains material relating to Oscar Wilde including correspondence with Vyvyan Holland, John H. Wheelock, and Allan Wade concerning Wilde and typescript copies and extracts of Wilde's letters located in other repositories which Brasol used for his book Oscar Wilde: the Man, the Artist, and the Martyr. The series also includes the printer's typescript draft with handwritten corrections of Brasol's translation of Diary of a Writer by Fyodor Dostoyevsky and material relating to Edgar Allan Poe including correspondence of the Edgar Allan Poe Society.
Brasol was purported to have aided in the translation of the American edition of the anti-Semitic tract The Protocols of the Elders of Zion, and the papers contain correspondence and related reference material exploring various Jewish issues in the Newspaper Clippings series. Brasol also participated in arranging a series of commentaries on the protocols that were to be published in Henry Ford's paper the Dearborn Independent. The Legal File contains correspondence and other papers concerning the legal case brought against Ford by Henry Bernstein, who, in 1921, had written a book exposing the protocols as fraudulent and sued Ford to retract their publication.
The Anti-Soviet Campaign series highlights efforts of White Russian émigrés to deny the Soviet Union official international recognition as the legitimate government of Russia.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eleven series:
Political Correspondence, 1922-1952
Personal Correspondence, 1934-1952
Anti-Soviet Campaign, 1919-1948
Scrapbook, 1927
Post-Revolutionary Russia, circa 1919-1922
Legal File, circa 1925-1950
Vladimir von Koeppen File, 1921-1927
Speeches, circa 1922-1930
Literary File, 1920-1954
Newspaper Clippings, circa 1919-1921
Addition, 1925-1941
Container List
- Political Correspondence, 1922-1952 (Box 1-6)
  Correspondence, publicity material, book reviews, political criticism.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Chronological file (Box 1)
    - 1922-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1933 (Box 2)
    - 1941-1944 (Box 3)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 4)
  - Publicity, book reviews, and political criticism (Box 5-6)
- Personal Correspondence, 1934-1952 (Box 7-11)
  Correspondence and miscellaneous material.
  - Chronological file (Box 7)
    - 1934 (Box 7)
    - 1934-1937 (Box 8)
    - 1948-1951 (Box 9)
    - 1949-1952 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 11)
- Anti-Soviet Campaign, 1919-1948 (Box 12-15)
  Correspondence and miscellaneous material concerning efforts to deny the Soviet Union official international recognition as the legitimate government of Russia.
  - 1919, 1933 (Box 12)
  - 1933-1935 (Box 13)
  - 1935 (Box 14)
  - 1935-1936, 1946-1948 (Box 15)
- Scrapbook, 1927 (Box 16)
  Scrapbook of clippings concerning Brasol's Elements of Crime (1927).
  - Scrapbook, 1927 (Box 16)
- Post-Revolutionary Russia, circa 1919-1922 (Box 17-22)
  Notebooks containing correspondence and miscellaneous material.
  Organized numerically by notebook number.
  - Nos. 7, 10, and 12 (Box 17)
  - Nos. 13 and 15-16 (Box 18)
  - Nos. 17-19 (Box 19)
  - Nos. 20-22 (Box 20)
  - Nos. 23-25 (Box 21)
  - No. 26 and unnumbered (Box 22)
- Legal File, circa 1925-1950 (Box 23-25)
  Correspondence, legal records, and miscellaneous material.
  Organized into two groups: Herman Bernstein v. Henry Ford and miscellaneous records
  - Herman Bernstein v. Henry Ford, circa 1925-1927 (Box 23-24)
  - Miscellaneous records, circa 1926-1950 (Box 25)
- Vladimir von Koeppen File, 1921-1927 (Box 26-32)
  Correspondence and miscellaneous material concerning Vladimir von Koeppen.
  - 1921-1927 (Box 26-32)
- Speeches, circa 1922-1930 (Box 33-34)
  Speeches.
  - circa 1922-1930 (Box 33-34)
- Literary File, 1920-1954 (Box 35-52)
  Correspondence, drafts, notes, proofs, typescripts, and miscellaneous material relating to Brasol's books, translations, and literary criticism.
  Arranged by subject or topic.
  - Books (Box 35)
    - Socialism and Civilization, 1920 (Box 35)
    - The World at the Crossroads, 1921 (Box 36)
    - The Mighty Three: Poushkin, Gogol, Dostoievsky, 1934 (Box 37)
    - Oscar Wilde: The Man, the Artist, and the Martyr (Box 38)
      - Photostats, 1938 (Box 38)
      - Correspondence (Box 39)
        - To 1954 (Box 39)
        - 1938 (Box 40)
  - Translations and miscellaneous writings (Box 41)
    - Cartwright, Beatrice, correspondence and notes concerning memoirs, 1944 (Box 41)
    - "The Nobel Dynasty," typescript, 1943 (Box 41)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor, Diary of a Writer, translated by Brasol (Box 42)
      - Draft (Box 42)
      - Draft and page proof (Box 43)
      - Miscellaneous material (Box 44)
    - Varneke, B. V., History of the Russian Theatre, draft and typescript of Brasol's translation, 1951 (Box 45)
    - "Walter Pater," correspondence, draft, and typescript 1946-1952 (Box 46-47)
    - "Avinoff: a Study in Genius," notes, 1952 (Box 48)
    - "Criminal Institutes on the Continent of Europe," draft (Box 49)
    - Sikorsky, "Ideas inspired by the Lord's Prayer" (Box 50)
  - Miracle Letter Club (Box 50)
  - Poe, Edgar Allan, correspondence concerning, 1920-1928, 1939, undated (Box 51-52)
- Newspaper Clippings, circa 1919-1921 (Box 53)
  Newspaper clippings mostly regarding Jewish topics.
  - circa 1919-1921 (Box 53)
- Addition, 1925-1941 (Box 54-64)
  Correspondence, articles, reports, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged by subject, topic, or type of material.
  - Correspondence (Box 54)
    - 1925-1927 (Box 54)
    - 1927-1928 (Box 55)
    - 1929-1931 (Box 56)
  - Social Science Abstracts, correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 56)
  - "Police Science in U.S.A.," 1930-1931 (Box 56)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1941 (Box 57)
  - "Crime, Criminology and Criminological Institute," correspondence, 1938 (Box 57)
  - "Methods of Criminal Investigation," English translation of Brasol's Russian text (Box 58)
  - National Crime Commission, 1927 (Box 58)
  - Columbia University, New York, N.Y., correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 59)
  - "Columbia Reports," 1929-1930, undated (Box 60)
  - "International Criminalistic Academy, International Congress," Lausanne, Switzerland, 1938 (Box 61)
  - "Police Scientifique Centers in Europe," 1926-1929 (Box 61)
  - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor, Diary of a Writer, translation by Brasol (Box 62-63)
  - Criminology, correspondence, articles, and reports (Box 63-64)